Guide to the Records of the Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland 1895-2021 MS 3034
New-York Historical Society
Records of the Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland
1895-2021
New-York Historical Society
Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland
MS 3034
31.41 Linear feet (in 31 record cartons and 1 document box).
Records of the still-active Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland, a lineage organization open to qualified women who descend from Dutch settlers present in New Netherlands 1674 and earlier. The Daughters of Holland Dames' objectives are to perpetuate the memory and promote the virtues of the Dutch settlers by collecting and preserving historical and genealogical documents, encouraging historical research and erecting durable memorials in lasting tribute to the early Dutch settlers. Examples are: stained glass windows to Peter Stuyvesant at St. Mark's Church-in-the-Bowery (1903), and to Henry Hudson at the New-York Historical Society (1908). Includes board minutes, financial records, correspondence, ephemera, and membership applications.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in this collection are stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Restriction: In transferring this collection to the New-York Historical Society, the Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland (DHD) stipulated that the material under "Subseries IV.B. Membership Applications and Genealogical Proofs, 1895-2019," containing membership applications, supplemental applications, and working proof files, "be made available for scholarly research... 100 years after that member's birth year" (birth data is recorded with a member's name and unique number on their application). As the New-York Historical Society cannot revisit the collection annually to determine which applications have passed a century and should be deemed open, interested researchers should contact the DHD for details: www.hollanddames.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland, 2015, 2019, 2021.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series:
Series I. Governance, 1895-2018
Subseries I.A. Founding documents, 1895-2006
Subseries I.B. Board Meeting minutes, 1895-2013
Subseries I.C. Reports, 1898-2012
Subseries I.D. Officers' files, 1919-2018 (bulk, 1992-2018)
Series II. Subject Files, 1892-2013
Subseries II.A. Meetings, luncheons, receptions, 1900-2013
Subseries II.B. Projects and general topics, 1896-2013
Subseries II.C. Talks & papers delivered before the Society & elsewhere, 1892-2013
Subseries II.D. Artifacts, circa 1898-1990s
Series III. Financial, 1896-2011
Subseries III.A. Treasurer's reports, correspondence, receipts, 1896-2011
Subseries III.B. Financial Statements & tax returns, 1964-2007
Subseries III.C. Banking and Investment records, 1938-2000
Subseries III.D. Miscellaneous financial records, 1898-1995
Series IV. Membership, 1895-2021
Subseries IV.A. Subseries IV.A. Membership registers, directories, record books, 1895-2021
Subseries IV.B. Membership Applications and Genealogical Proofs, 1895-2021 (RESTRICTED)
Historical Note
The Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland (DHD), was organized on 8 May 1895 and incorporated 9 December 1895 "to perpetuate the memory and promote the principles and virtues of the Dutch ancestors of its members" by collecting and preserving "genealogical and historical documents relating to the Dutch in America," encouraging "excellence in historical research," and establishing "commemorative and durable memorials in lasting tribute to the early Dutch settlers." Similar in aim to the males-only Holland Society of New York (established 1885), the DHD is open solely to women over the age of eighteen who can prove descent from an ancestor, male or female, who was born in the Netherlands or New Netherland prior to the 1674 Treaty of Westminster (when the Dutch ceded control of the region to the English), or whose ancestor resided in New Netherland prior to the Treaty of Westminster, or whose ancestor held some official capacity in New Netherland (e.g., a Director General; a member of the Director General's council; a member of a governmental or religious body; a patroon or freeholder; a commissioner of Indian Affairs, boundaries, or treaties; or a commissioned officer, soldier, or sailor who served in defense of New Netherland).
In fulfillment of its goals the DHD has placed Dutch-specific monuments around New York City, most notably at St. Mark's Church-in-the-Bowery, where a stained glass window to Peter Stuyvesant (1610-1672), last Director General of New Netherland, was installed above his burial vault in 1903, and at the New-York Historical Society, where a stained glass window entitled "Memorial to Henry Hudson: The Arrival of the Halve Maen, 1609," was installed in the library in 1908. (The DHD later funded the restoration of both windows.)
From 1915 through the 1990s the DHD provided partial scholarships to American college students of Dutch ancestry. They have supported Dutch historic sites in New York City, such as the 18th-century Hendrick I. Lott House in Marine Park, Brooklyn, and the Brinckerhoff Cemetery, a colonial-era burial ground in Fresh Meadows, Queens. The DHD has hosted visits of the Dutch royal family (by tradition its female members have been honorary Holland Dames), and participated in anniversary celebrations, such as the 2009 Henry Hudson Quadricentennial/NY400, in recognition of their Dutch ancestors.
The Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland governing board is headed by its Directress General. The following women have held that position through 2020 (their membership numbers appear after their names):
Directresses General, 1895-2020
1895-1898
Mrs. William Gihon (Caroline Remsen) [3]
1899-1902
Miss Margaret Sophia Remsen [14]
1903-1906
Mrs. Eugene A. Hoffman (Mary Crooke Elmendorf) [10]
1907-1909
Mrs. Frederick Hasbrouck (Melinda Harriet Van Voorst) [39]
1910-1912
Mrs. D. Phoenix Ingraham (Frances Adelaide Leverich) [80]
1913-1916
Mrs. William Tod Helmuth (Fannie Ida Pritchard) [103]
1917-1920
Mrs. James Allan MacDonald (Cara Crooke) [169]
1921-1924
Mrs. Wright Prescott Edgerton (Fannie Helmuth) [153]
1925-1928
Miss Margaret Augusta Jackson [78]
1929-1932
Miss Louise Capron Rapalje [170]
1933-1935
Mrs. Russell Evans Tucker (Clara deRussy Nichols) [255]
1936-1937
Mrs. John Henry MacCracken (Edith Constable) [362]
1938-1941
Mrs. William Henry Sage (Amelia Whitney) [317]
1942-1945
Mrs. John Henry MacCracken (Edith Constable) [362]
1946-1950
Mrs. Irving L. Cabot (Ida Livingston Hagedorn) [418]
1951-1952
Mrs. C. Herbert Appleby (Leila Alice Varet) [466]
1952-1957
Mrs. Quinto Maganini (Margaretta Mason Kingsbury) [460]
1958-1961
Mrs. Robert Leighton Crawford (Leila Alice Varet) [466]
1962-1965
Mrs. John Kean (Mary-Alice Barney) [472]
1966-1969
Mrs. Hoyte Joyce (Anne Hoyte Hicks) [507]
1970-1973
Mrs. Franklin Bache Satterthwaite (Emily Vaux Cresson) [494]
1974-1977
Mrs. William Halsted Savage (Carolyn Bleecker Mackie) [545]
1978-1981
Miss Catherine Cary [588]
1982-1987
Mrs. William Jay Brennan Jr. (Lucy Curley Joyce) [530]
1988-1991
Mrs. Charles James Irwin (Jane Remsen Darlington) [589]
1992-1995
Mrs. Dennis Daughtry McCrary (Eugenia Potts Lester) [606]
1996-2001
Mrs. Alexander O. Vietor (Anna Glen Butler) [597]
2002-2008
Mrs. Ernest P. Brinkley (Barbara Alice Andrews) [673]
2008-2011
Mrs. Lee Crandall Park (Mary Elizabeth Woodfill) [699]
2011-2017
Mrs. Peter Kimmelman (Elbrun Eileen Russell-French) [683]
2017-2020
Dr. Suzanne Roff, PhD [784]
[Adapted from Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland: Historical Records, 1895-2017, Including Reprints of the Society's Original Record Books, and Register of Members, 1895-2019. For information on the current activities of the Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland, visit www.hollanddames.org.]
Related Archival Materials
A 1664 deed (in Dutch) issued by Peter Stuyvesant, as Director General of New Netherland, to Govert Loockermans for land at Canarsie (now in Brooklyn), and an accompanying frame, made of wood from the pear tree Stuyvesant planted at what became the northeast corner of Third Avenue and East 13th Street in Manhattan, were given to the Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland by Mrs. William E. (Emma Du Puy) Reed (ca. 1871-1962), a descendant of Loockermans, in 1933. The Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland transferred both to the New-York Historical Society in 2015. They are cataloged as Y-AHMC - Stuyvesant deed (oversize small).
Scope and Contents
The records of the Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland span from 1895, the year of the organization's founding, through 2019. Within the Society, each officer kept her own records, and reported the activities in her purview monthly or annually. As a result, and because the Society's records were never maintained in a central location, there are decided gaps in coverage. Despite this, the minutes of board and annual meetings provide the best documentation of the DHD's activities and projects, some of which are further detailed in dedicated folders. See, for instance, the papers generated by the 1903 installation of a stained glass window to Peter Stuyvesant in St. Mark's Church-in-the-Bowery (box 9, folder 18), or the memorial to Society's communal Dutch ancestors proposed for Battery Park, and the ensuing litigation brought by its designer, sculptor Robert Aitken, who sued for payment (box 8, folder 12).
The collection includes applications for membership in the DHD, which document the lineage of each member back to her qualifying ancestor(s). Supplemental applications provide similar information for additional ancestors from whom members descend. Restrictions apply to this portion of the collection; see the note at "Subseries IV.B. Membership Applications and Genealogical Proofs, 1895-2019," in the container list, below.
Separated Materials
In 1992 Mrs. Mildred Toombs of Port Saint Lucie, Florida, donated to the Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland an anonymous Revolutionary War diary and tune book dated 1781-1782. This came to the New-York Historical Society with the records of the Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland, but because it has no bearing on the operations and activities of the organization, it is cataloged separately as AHMC - Revolutionary War diary.
Dutch Americans -- Societies, etc.; Women -- Societies and clubs -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (State) -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 -- Societies, etc.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Invitations.; Membership application.; Minutes (administrative records); Photographs.; Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland -- Archives
- Series I. Governance, 1895-2018
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized in four subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Founding documents, 1895-2006
  Subseries I.B. Board Meeting minutes, 1895-2013
  Subseries I.C. Reports, 1898-2012
  Subseries I.D. Officers' files, 1919-2018 (bulk, 1992-2018)
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes the foundational documents of the Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland: its certificate of incorporation (1895), printed constitutions and by-laws; meeting minutes of its governing board; annual reports; and officers' files. The officers' files (bulk, 1992-2012), appear to have been assembled by DHD board members, each of whom kept her own records as part of her duties. These include postal and email correspondence, invitations, ceremonial programs, drafts of board minutes, clippings, photographs, and ephemera, such as an orange handkerchief dated "09.09.09" given to invited guests to wave in celebration of the opening of the New Amsterdam Pavilion in Battery Park by Crown Prince (now King) Willem-Alexander of the Netherlands (see box 7, folder 13). The list of Directresses General in the historical note near the start of this finding aid may assist researchers wishing to interpret the material in the officers' files.
  - Subseries I.A. Founding documents, 1895-2006
    - Certificate of Incorporation, Constitution, By-Laws, Members (1-128) [bound volume], 1895-1909 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Certificate of Incorporation, 1895 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Incorporation documents [copies], 1909, 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
      Includes a copy of a petition to the New York State Supreme Court (1909) to change the name of the organization from "Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of the State of New York" to "Society of Daughters of Holland Dames, Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Families of New Netherland."
    - Constitutional amendments, 1923-1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Constitution and By-Laws [published], 1926-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries I.B. Board Meeting minutes, 1895-2013
    - Minutes [bound volume], 1895-1901 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Minutes | board of managers [bound volume], 1901-1906 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Minutes [bound volume], 1902-1913 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Minutes [bound volume], 1906-1916 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Minutes [bound volume], 1913-1923 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Minutes [bound volume], 1923-1933 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Minutes [bound volume], 1934-1944 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, 1944-1949 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, 1950-1954 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 1955-1959 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, 1960-1965 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    - Minutes, 1966-1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
      Includes annual reports, 1970-1974.
    - Minutes, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
      Lacks annual meetings, 1972-1973.
    - Minutes, 1976-1977, 1979-1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    - Minutes, 1982-1984 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - Minutes, 1985-1987 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
    - Minutes, 1986-1990 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
      Scope and Contents Note
      Includes annual report, 1985.
    - Minutes, 1989-1993 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, 1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
    - Minutes, 1993-1994 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
    - Minutes, 1995-1997 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, 1998-2003 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 2004-2007 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, 2007-2010 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    - Minutes, 2010-2011 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 2011-2012 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    - Minutes, 2012-2013 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
  - Subseries I.C. Reports, 1898-2012
    - Annual reports, 1898-1907 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    - Annual reports, 1908-1918 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
    - Annual reports, 1919-1932 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    - Annual reports, 1933-1947 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
    - Annual reports, 1956-1962 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
    - Annual reports, 1963-1971 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
    - Annual reports, 1972-1981 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
    - Annual reports, 1982-1992 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
    - Annual reports, 1993-2001 (Offsite-box 4-A, Folder 1)
    - Annual reports, 2002-2009 (Offsite-box 4-A, Folder 2)
    - Annual reports, 2010, 2012 (Offsite-box 4-A, Folder 3)
    - Historian's reports [bound volume], 1929 December - 1933 (Offsite-box 4-A, Folder 4)
    - Historian's reports [bound volume], 1936-1939 (Offsite-box 4-A, Folder 5)
    - Recording Secretary's notebook, 1974 (Offsite-box 4-A, Folder 6)
    - [Recording Secretary's notebook?], 1986-1990 (Offsite-box 4-A, Folder 7)
  - Subseries I.D. Officers' files, 1919-2018 (bulk, 1992-2018)
    - Officers' files | general, 1992 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
    - Officers' files | general, 1993 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
    - Officers' files | general, 1994 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10)
    - Officers' files | general, 1995 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 11)
    - Officers' files | general, 1996 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 12)
    - Officers' files | general (2 folders), 1997 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 13-14)
    - Officers' files | general, 1998 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 15)
    - Officers' files | general, 1999 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 16)
    - Officers' files | general, 2000 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 17)
    - Officers' files | general (2 folders), 2001 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 18-19)
    - Officers' files | Martha Glass binder, 1992-1996 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
    - Officers' files | binder [white] marked "Holland Dames Outings" (2 folders), circa 1993-2003 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2-3)
    - Officers' files | binder [white] marked "Holland Dames" (2 folders), [2000] (Offsite-box 7, Folder 4-5)
    - Officers' files | binder [green] marked "Holland Dames Activities" (3 folders), 2000-2008 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 6-8)
    - Officers' files | Mary Park, 2008-2015 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1-27)
      Topics include: Annual Reports; NY400 events; stained glass windows at the New-York Historical Society and St. Mark's Church-in-the-Bowery; Marisol DeLuna's scarf designed for DHD; Dutch research guide; DHD website; biographical information on DHD members and Directresses General.
    - Officers' files | Mary Park, 1990-2016 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1-14)
      Topics include: Dutch Royal family; replica ship "Half Moon"; St. Nicholas Society; Holland Society; DHD newsletters (scattered issues, 2005-2016).
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman, 2008 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9)
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman: DHD scarf (2 folders), 2008-2009 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 10-11)
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman: Directress General's mailings, 2009-2011 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman, 2009 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman, 2010 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman (3 folders), 2011 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15-17)
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman (11 folders), 2011 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 15-25)
      Topics include: List of members and associates with Constitution and By-Laws; Nomination Committee; Meeting Schedule for 5 Dutch Days; Changes to DHD Board Directory; Board Meeting; Annual Meeting (April 21, 2011); Board Meeting (September 14, 2011); Directress General Luncheon (October 25, 2011); Board Meeting (November 18, 2011); Fast Facts; By-Law Committee; Miscellaneous Emails.
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman (5 folders), 2012 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-5)
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman (9 folders), 2012 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 26-34)
      Topics include: Recording Secretary's Minutes (April 17, 2012 - December 8, 2013); Minutes of the Board (April 19, 2012); Nominating Committee; Annual Meeting (April 19, 2012); Martha Glass Lecture on Ceramics Collection; Board Meetings (September 12, October 18, and December 9, 2012); Unveiling Restored Stuyvesant Window at St. Mark's Church (November 16, 2012).
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman, 2013 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 1-13)
      Topics include: Board Meeting (March 28, 2013); DHD Member Profiles (Elbrun Kimmelman, Mary Van Buren, Firth Fabend, Pamela Meyjes); Social Register article; Board Meetings (September 12 and 27, 2013); Board Meeting at Home of Mrs. Thomas E. Slattery (October 4, 2013); Board Meeting (October 23, 2013); Frick Collection Tour and Luncheon (November 14, 2013); Board Meeting and Christmas Party (December 22, 2013); Paper "Windows on Dutch History" by Elbrun Kimmelman; Annual Meeting & Tea (April 24, 2013); Paas Heritage Ball.
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman, 2014 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 14-23)
      Topics include: List of Members and Associates with Constitution and By-Laws; By-Law Revision; Making of a new, larger flag; Board Meeting (March 27, 2014); Annual Meeting (April 23, 2014); Board Meeting (September 29, 2014); Washington D.C. Trip (October 25, 2014); Board Meeting and Christmas Party (December 7, 2014); Paas Heritage Ball.
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman, 2015 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 1-15)
      Topics include: By-law Revision; "Windows on Dutch History" by Elbrun Kimmelman; Board Meeting (March 4, 2015); Annual Meeting (May 1, 2015); Board Meetings (June 1, September 21, and October 29, 2015); Board Meeting and Christmas Party (December 11, 2015); Paas Heritage Ball; DHD Gift of Loockermans Deed with Stuyvesant signature and pear tree frame to New-York Historical Society.
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman (6 folders), 2016 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 17-22)
      Topics include: List of members and associates with constitution and by-laws; DHD news, promotion, membership; Board meetings (June 8, September 19, and October 27, 2016); "A Bit of Dutch Thanksgiving," paper by Elbrun Kimmelman; Board meeting and Christmas party (December 4, 2016).
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman (7 folders), 2016 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1-7)
      Topics include: Board meeting (March 16, 2016); Annual meeting (April 29, 2016); DHD newsletter (Spring 2016); St. Mark's Window paper, as deliverd in 2016; Registration chair's anniversary contribution; Paas Heritage ball.
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman, 2017 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 8-16)
      Topics include: DHD news, promotion membership; Board meetings (March 3 and 27, 2017); Grant recipient, Artyom Anikin; Introduction to Historical Records Book, 1895-2017, by Elbrun Kimmelman; Anniversary Book; Annual meeting (May 5, 2017); Board meeting (October 26, 2017); Directress General lunch photos; budget; Trip to Susan Durkee's (May 2017); Paas Heritage Ball; Anniversary Book: Historic Record, 1895-2017; Grant Document for Short-Term Fellowship.
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman, 2018 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 17-20)
      Topics include: List of members and associates with constitution and by-laws; Short-term fellowship report, Marian Leech; Paas Heritage Ball; Board resume.
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman: Files Including Various Project Notes By Project (24 folders), 2010-2017 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 21-44)
      Topics include: Anna Glenn Vietor, Directress General, last letter at 89; Ellan Thorsan's sources, Corresponding Secretary; Life membership discussions; Honorary & diplomatic members -- Correspondence with the Queen of the Netherlands; Awards and Recognition; Directress General Star Recognition; Klomp Award; DHD Pear Award; News about DHD -- Related articles & clippings; Communications and promotions; DHD brochure; DHD publications; DHD Ad Hoc Technology and Website committee.
    - Officers' files | Elbrun Kimmelman: Files Including Various Project Notes By Project (40 folders), 2015-2018, undated (Offsite-box 19, Folder 1-40)